<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom's Blog - projects</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/projects.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2017-08-21T12:30:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Kniterate Post KickStarter</title><link href="/projects/kniterate-post-kickstarter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-21T10:01:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-21T12:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Tom Catling</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-08-21:/projects/kniterate-post-kickstarter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I have been back in China again making knitting machines with Kniterate. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; We concluded our Kickstarter campaign in May and raised a whopping $636k! We have since redesigned the electronics of the machine to be a bit more industrial and I took a few weeks away from work in the UK in August to go over to the factory near Shanghai and integrate the new boards into the prototype. I have also rewritten the firmware to be a lot faster and more modular/manageable. I learned a lot about RS485, acceleration profiles, interrupts and various board-board communication standards during this process!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I have been back in China again making knitting machines with Kniterate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We concluded our Kickstarter campaign in May and raised a whopping $636k! We have since redesigned the electronics of the machine to be a bit more industrial and I took a few weeks away from work in the UK in August to go over to the factory near Shanghai and integrate the new boards into the prototype. I have also rewritten the firmware to be a lot faster and more modular/manageable. I learned a lot about RS485, acceleration profiles, interrupts and various board-board communication standards during this process!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not supposed to post any pictures of the machine innards here, so here is a small collection of pictures summarising my time in China instead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next task will be to work on the backend algorithms which allow us to go between a user-intelligble design file and machine code - what we call 'k-code.' The electronics and firmware are both now in a state where it makes sense to hand them over to new people to spread the knowledge around. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already written some basic slicing algorithms which we used in the campaign to make the garments shown below. On the left is our first six-colour sample with the corresponding technical face, and on the right are some garments we made in a collaboration with the very cool Lindsay Degen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slicing for knitting is a really interesting problem and potentially very complex. The examples given below are about as simple as it gets: flat double-knit with minimal shaping and no fancy stitches. Initially we must limit the users freedom to make it manageable, but in the future I would love to work on some kind of generalised solution (similar to &lt;a href="https://www.disneyresearch.com/publication/machine-knitting-compiler/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; awesome paper from Disney Research).&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>