<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Tom's Blog - Tom Catling</title><link>/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Allotment Party!</title><link>/life/allotment-party.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We had an allotment party!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Tom Catling</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:None,2019-05-05:/life/allotment-party.html</guid><category>update</category><category>allotment</category></item><item><title>From Weebly to GitHub</title><link>/coding/from-weebly-to-github.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm in the process of moving my &lt;a href="https://tomcatling.weebly.com/"&gt;old blog&lt;/a&gt; across from Weebly to Pelican on GitHub. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Tom Catling</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:None,2019-05-04:/coding/from-weebly-to-github.html</guid><category>update</category></item><item><title>Tunebook Modernisation with LaTeX and ABC</title><link>/coding/tunebook-modernisation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been doing some calling and playing with the UCLU Ceilidh Band recently. Our tunebook is a much-edited PDF that has been handed down through generations of students. Some pages are scans of photocopies, annotated by hand and becoming fairly illegible. PDF doesn't understand music so it's impossible to edit notes or transpose things. I am also forever losing pages and entire copies because I normally print it out in a rush and don't have time to bind it. When I do have a copy it's normally mixed up and very difficult to find a certain tune...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/messy_tune.png" alt="Messy tune image" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter ABC notation! This is a pretty old-school text format for music, and many of the tunes in our book are already written out in ABC on sites like thesession.org. ABC was introduced in the early 90s and has since become pretty sophisticated. It's designed to be human readable (some musicians can sight read ABC as fluently as sheet music) and is more than sufficient for transcribing tunes with chords and a couple of different parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Cooley&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reel&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;​&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;M&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Edor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;|:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;GF&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;EBBA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;EB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;AB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;G&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dBAG&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;FDAD&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;G&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;BD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;AD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;FDAD&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Bm7&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dAFD&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;EBBA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;EB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;AB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;G&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;defg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Bm&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;afec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Bm7&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dBAF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DEFD&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;E2&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="o"&gt;:|&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="n"&gt;gf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;eB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;efge&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;eB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;G&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gedB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;A2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;FA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;DAFA&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;A2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;FA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Bm&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;defg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;eB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;eBgB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;eB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;B2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;G&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;defg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Bm&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;afec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Bm7&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dBAF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;D&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DEFD&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Em&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;E2&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="o"&gt;:|&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/cooleys.png" alt="Cooleys" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining this with LaTeX and the CTAN ABC package to generate sheet music allows me to create a tunebook that can be rebuilt with a single command. Here it is on GitHub! (still a work in progress)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All tune sets are stored in ABC format in separate files to allow for easy editing, and it's even possible to transpose pieces easily with tools like mandolintab. The table of contents at the start is automatically regenerated, images inserted etc. LaTeX is great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found original high-resolution images where possible and even touched up the front cover. I intend to make five or so hardcover copies to keep with the band so we always have decent music to read from. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to do some experimenting with gluing a printed cover onto mounting board. Final copies will be printed double-sided, but the above images give you an idea of what it will look like. Very satisfying!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Tom Catling</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:None,2017-11-19:/coding/tunebook-modernisation.html</guid><category>music</category><category>.abc</category><category>automation</category></item><item><title>Kniterate Post KickStarter</title><link>/projects/kniterate-post-kickstarter.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, I have been back in China again making knitting machines with Kniterate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We concluded our Kickstarter campaign in May and raised a whopping $636k! We have since redesigned the electronics of the machine to be a bit more industrial and I took a few weeks away from work in the UK in August to go over to the factory near Shanghai and integrate the new boards into the prototype. I have also rewritten the firmware to be a lot faster and more modular/manageable. I learned a lot about RS485, acceleration profiles, interrupts and various board-board communication standards during this process!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not supposed to post any pictures of the machine innards here, so here is a small collection of pictures summarising my time in China instead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next task will be to work on the backend algorithms which allow us to go between a user-intelligble design file and machine code - what we call 'k-code.' The electronics and firmware are both now in a state where it makes sense to hand them over to new people to spread the knowledge around. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already written some basic slicing algorithms which we used in the campaign to make the garments shown below. On the left is our first six-colour sample with the corresponding technical face, and on the right are some garments we made in a collaboration with the very cool Lindsay Degen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slicing for knitting is a really interesting problem and potentially very complex. The examples given below are about as simple as it gets: flat double-knit with minimal shaping and no fancy stitches. Initially we must limit the users freedom to make it manageable, but in the future I would love to work on some kind of generalised solution (similar to &lt;a href="https://www.disneyresearch.com/publication/machine-knitting-compiler/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; awesome paper from Disney Research).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Tom Catling</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 10:01:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:None,2017-08-21:/projects/kniterate-post-kickstarter.html</guid><category>kniterate</category><category>china</category><category>kickstarter</category><category>update</category></item><item><title>UCLO &amp; OSL</title><link>/life/uclo-and-osl.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've started working as a technician at University College London Observatory and in the Optical Science Lab (where I did my PhD, also in UCL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's pretty varied and interesting. We're assembling the corrector optics for DESI at the moment in OSL. This is a big job; there are 6 lenses which are each about 1m in diameter, all of which have to be aligned accurately to within ~10 microns. There is a lot of fiddly manual work involved in this, as well as a lot of thought about measurements, sources of error and co-ordinate systems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the observatory I am partly responsible for looking after the site as a whole, so I've done a lot of general work like fixing lights and working with contractors, but also some technical stuff when the various telescopes inevitably stop working or need new features. The Radcliffe in particular is showing it's age and needs an update/overhaul in the near future. It is a relatively complex system controlled entirely by 80s-era electronics on massive cards in a wardrobe-sized control box. Although it is quite unique in it's age and ability to acquire targets automatically, I suspect it is not the only telescope which suffers from problems due to outdated technology and lack of funds for maintenance.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with this has been an interesting lesson on longevity and obsolescence. How can you design something to work for 10+ years when you have no idea what kind of protocols and technology will even exist so far ahead? Will we still have USB? Ethernet? It is impressive that the control system still works at all in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was designed to be modular and upgradable, but paradigm shifts within automation and control across the 20+ years since it was built mean that this has become difficult despite the best efforts of the designer (Dr Peter Thomas, who wrote his thesis on automating the Radcliffe in the early 90s, did an excellent job). For instance, even replacing a stepper motor driver becomes an ordeal. Computation was expensive back in the 90s, so it was pretty normal to send a full-speed step sequence to a driver and have it physically buffer and slow down the sequence to provide an acceleration profile. I had never heard of this before, because it is so easy now to compute the acceleration (and everything else) centrally...  Anyway, the Radcliffe probably deserves it's own post sometime in the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got an allotment just next to the observatory, and have been enjoying gardening despite being entirely new to it. I have a big plot (10 poles!) but inherited several fruit trees and left a decent amount unplanted, so it hasn't been overwhelming. I often go there at lunchtime with some soup and do a bit of weeding. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Tom Catling</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:None,2017-04-10:/life/uclo-and-osl.html</guid><category>update</category><category>allotment</category></item><item><title>New Job, New Beginnings</title><link>/life/new-job-new-beginnings.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing the trend (but hopefully signalling the end) of large delays between updates, I thought I should post something. A lot has happened recently: I have a job and I'm moving off the boat. This is a little bit sad as it means the end of a lot of freedom, but I am also excited about both things because of stuff that I have been missing, such as a healthy work/life balance and hot water on demand. My friend took this photo and sent it to me, but I don't want to upload it to Facebook and tag myself in it, so I will post it here instead because I think it is a nice picture that commemorates my boat-PhD life of the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/whatsapp-image-2017-01-28-at-16-28-58_orig.jpeg" alt="On the boat" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately Triangle will have to go and live in Sheffield for a while, but we will be reunited eventually.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Tom Catling</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:None,2017-02-06:/life/new-job-new-beginnings.html</guid><category>update</category></item></channel></rss>